Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VI: The Cuban Excludables, 1989-1997
  - Vuelo Llegas y Entrevista con Olimpio Guagua, circa 1990s; cuid17852 (Box 15, Cassette ref342)
    This video contains an interview with Olimpio Guagua, an officer in the Cuban Interior Ministry, as he awaits the arrival of a flight of deportees from the United States. Guagua describes his job responsibilities and the transfer of custody of the detained men from the United States to Cuba. The video also includes footage of the plane's descent and landing as well as the transfer of the prisoners. The video ends with brief interviews with the prisoners discussing their time in the United States and their feelings about being deported.
  - Martineau, Bolivar: Interview, circa 1990s; cuid17872 (Box 5, Betacam ref365)
  - Jorge, Luis, and Daniel, 1992 November 11; cuid17881 (Box 18, Cassette ref407)
    Test pattern with background conversations in Spanish. Cutaway shots of two men, some background direction in Spanish.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:03:00.
  - "Pablito Arayo", 1992 November 11; cuid17882 (Box 12, Cassette ref408)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:30.
    This video contains interviews with Pablo Arayo's family. Pablo had been living in the United States and was recently returned to Cuba as an excludable. His family shares their thoughts about his time away and their plans to visit him in the detention center. There is also an interview with Pablito Arayo, Pablo's son. The video ends with cutaway shots of Pablito and the Arayo family.
  - Interview Grandparents Guillermino, circa 1990s; cuid17891 (Box 19, Cassette ref480)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:17.
    This video contains interviews with five different grandparents who have children and grandchildren in the United States. The interviewer asks them about how they maintain relationships with their family amidst the political challenges between the United States and Cuba.
  - Plane arriving (B-roll), circa 1990s; cuid17894 (Box 80, Dvd ref336)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:47:00.
  - Cuba, Birmingham Airport (B-roll?), circa 1990s; cuid17898 (Box 49, Cassette ref1140)
  - "Demo 14 min Excludables", circa 1990s; cuid17901 (Box 4, U-matic ref638)
- Series VII: Cubans in Peru, 1982
  This series contains a small amount of footage related to the documentary Cubans in Peru. The1982 film presents the experiences and views of some of the Cubans who took part in the occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana in 1980. Videos from this documentary include footage of refugees in Tupac Amaru Stadium, interviews with Cuban political refugees, and footage of a Peruvian doctor who saved the life of a Cuban child. The scenes of the doctor and child are featured at the end of the documentary.
  - "Cubans in Peru DV#3", 1982; cuid785 (Box 55, Cassette ref1271)
    This video is 20 minutes in length, and most likely contains footage rather than the full-length documentary.
  - Children's Hospital and Tupac Amaru Park (B-roll), circa 1990; cuid17729 (Box 98, Dvd ref1301)
    This video features exterior footage of a children's hospital and Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. This video has no audio.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:06:23.
  - Tupac Amaru Park: Footage, circa 1982; cuid786 (Box 96, Dvd ref1314)
    Tupac Amaru Park is a sports complex in East Lima that became a refugee camp for Cubans who were granted asylum in Peru after their 1980 occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana.
    This video contains footage of Cuban exiles living in a tent city in Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. The video shows footage of concerned Peruvians speaking through a fence to the Cubans living in the park. It also includes some brief interviews with several Cubans living in the park about why they are there. Other footage features demonstrations and on-the-street interviews with Peruvians who oppose the presence of the Cuban exiles in the park as well as shots of local police in riot gear at the entrance to the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:31.
  - "Corvacho child Dr. Montano Peru", circa 1982; cuid17904 (Box 52, Cassette ref1211)
  - Mama del Niño, undated; cuid18779 (Box 26, Cassette 600)
    This video contains an interview with a Cuban woman living in Peru who has a son in a hospital in Cuba. She discusses the difficulties she faces trying to get passports and visas for herself and her children so that she could seek better medical care in either Brazil or the United States.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:15.
  - Peruvian Doctors: Interview about Cuban Child, circa 1982; cuid17905 (Box 98, Dvd ref1222)
    This video features an interview with two Peruvian doctors about a young Cuban boy in their care. They explain that the boy's mother had taken him from Cuba to Peru because she believed that he would get better medical care there. The doctors, however, explain that the boy has a complicated heart condition that they cannot treat. They discuss Peru's limited medical resources, and the need to send patients with more complicated medical issues to hospitals and clinics in Brazil. They explain they are only able to offer palliative care to the boy, and that he will need to go to another hospital for surgery.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:21.
  - University of San Marcos: Presentation on Embajador En Cuba, circa 1982; cuid787 (Box 95, Dvd ref711)
    This video begins with footage of a panel discussion at the University of San Marcos with scholars and diplomats discussing the relationship between Cuba and Peru, and the book Embajador en Cuba by Peruvian Ambassador Edgardo de Habich. At the end of the panel discussion Habich speaks briefly about his book before the footage ends. Microphones used during the panel create echo sounds in the auditorium, which make audio quality poor in various places. At minute 11:43 the footage changes to a brief interview with Habich in which he discusses the occupation of Tupac Amaru Park in Lima by Cuban Refugees, and the refugee status of the Cubans in the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:13.
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002
  The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of its leader, Fidel Castro. Because so much of the interview footage for Fidel: The Untold Story could not be included in the initial feature-length film, Estela and Ernesto Bravo made a follow-up documentary, Anecdotes about Fidel, in 2010. It includes portions of 24 interviews and expands on the stories about Fidel Castro.
  In 2001, Fidel: The Untold Story was selected for the Toronto Film Festival and won an award for "Distinguished Achievement for Excellence in Documentary Filmmaking" at the Urbanworld Film Festival in New York.
  This series contains clips, interviews, and background footage from the documentaries Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel. The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of leader, Fidel Castro. This series contains copies of both films. It includes complete interviews and portions of interviews highlighted in the two films. They feature historians, public figures, close friends, and Castro himself, and provide a glimpse into the life and personality of the Cuban leader. Interviewees include Alice Walker, Gabriel García Márquez, Arthur Schlesinger, Ramsey Clark, Ted Turner, Nelson Mandela, Charles Rangel, George McGovern, Philip Agee, and many others who share personal anecdotes along with political and historical perspectives.
  The anecdotes come not only from well-known Americans such as Harry Belafonte, Jesse Jackson, Angela Davis, Hank Aaron, Sydney Pollack and others, but also from many Cubans who are not well known in the United States. Among them are government officials and friends of Fidel such as Juan Almeida, Melba Hernández. Alfredo Guevara, Jorge Risquet, Antonio Núñez Jiménez, Alicia Alonso, Angela Castro, and Aleida Guevara.
  This series also contains a number of interviews that are not seen in the films. They include discussions with Hortensia Bussi de Allende, the widow of Salvador Allende, and American lawyer Victor Rabinowitz.
  Footage in this series also consists of clips from the Cuban State Council Archives and various news sources. Videos containing State Council footage often represent a wide date range. Some of the footage is dated 1998 which reflects the date the material was obtained, not the actual date of the events. The original dates of the footage were not recorded. Additional footage depicts Fidel Castro at a number of public events giving speeches or speaking with world leaders. Other materials in this series include documents related to the promotion and distribution of Fidel, including contact lists, posters, correspondence related to distribution rights.
  - Fidel: The Untold Story, 2000; cuid17906 (Reel ref1903_01, Reel ref1903_02, Reel ref1903_03, Reel ref1903_04, Reel ref1903_05, Reel ref1903_06, Reel ref1903_07, Reel ref1903_08, Reel ref1903_09, Reel ref1903_10, Reel ref1903_11, Reel ref1903_12, Reel ref1903_13, Reel ref1903_14, Reel ref1903_15, Reel ref1903_16, Reel ref1903_17, Reel ref1903_18)
    This is a full-length version of the film Fidel: The Untold Story. The complete documentary is contained on 6 positive film reels, 6 film negative reels, and 6 sound track reels.
  - "Fidel Trailer", circa 2000; cuid17907 (Box 46, Cassette ref1049)
  - An Evening with Estela Bravo: Filmmaker of "Fidel: The Untold Story" and "Anecdotes about Fidel" at the Paley Center for Media, New York City, 2012 May 9; cuid17909 (Box 73, Dvd 16)
    A film of the event honoring Estela Bravo, focusing on the release of Anecdotes about Fidel at the Paley Center for Media. Bravo speaks with Pat Mitchell about her life and career, and responds to questions from the audience. Clips are shown from Anecdotes about Fidel; There are also clips from other films that have dealt with Cuban-American relations, such as Miami-Havana, The Cuban Excludables, and Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba.
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17912 (Box 68, Cassette ref846, Box 83, Dvd ref846)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:42.
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid291 (Box 95, Dvd ref983)
    This video features an interview with baseball player Hank Aaron. At the beginning, Aaron briefly introduces himself and discusses his baseball career. The bulk of the interview focuses on Aaron's impression of Cuba and Fidel Castro. Aaron describes traveling to Cuba to film a documentary about Cuban baseball players, and describes the quality of education and baseball training he observed while in Cuba. He also discusses meeting Fidel Castro, and speaks specifically about Castro's athletic ability. Aaron also talks briefly about the poor diplomatic relations between Cuba and the United States, and argues that lack of trade and freedom of movement between the countries has contributed to the suffering of Cuban people and their family members in the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:01.
  - Agee, Philip: Interview, 1997 March 8
    - Agee, Philip: Interview Recording, 1997 March 8; cuid17913; 4 items This interview is contained on 4 access DVDs (Box 75, Dvd ref15)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 4 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:29:22; Part 2 - 00:08:00; Part 3 - 00:00:09; Part 4 - 00:01:25.
      In this interview Philip Agee begins by talking about his work for the CIA and the fallout after the publication of his book Inside the Company. He discusses his opinions about Fidel Castro and interest in Cuban life and culture. For the bulk of the interview he talks about United States policy toward Cuba and CIA efforts to overthrow Fidel Castro. He also touches on controversy surrounding the Kennedy assassination and discusses Americans' views about the Cuban revolution.
    - Agee, Philip: Interview Transcript, cuid17914
  - Agee, Philip: Interview Transcript, undated; cuid17915 (Box 72, Folder 13)
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, 1998 November 21; cuid292 (Box 96, Dvd ref1047)
    Ricardo Alarcon de Quesada (1937 - ) is a Cuban statesman who served as Cuba's Permanent Representative to the United Nations for nearly 30 years. He was Cuba's Minister of Foreign Affairs from 1992-1993 and President of the National Assembly of People's Power from 1993-2013. During his time at the UN, Alarcon held several leading offices, such as Vice President of the General Assembly.
    This video features a portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón. At the beginning of the interview Alarcón discusses the political and diplomatic positions he has held within the Cuban government, including President of the National Assembly and United Nations ambassador. He discusses receiving the appointment of UN ambassador at the age of 28, and his inexperience in that position. He also describes meeting Fidel Castro for the first time when Castro's revolutionary forces entered Havana in January 1959. The bulk of the interview focuses on Alarcón's memories of Havana during the revolutionary period and the uncertainty during those years.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:08.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, 1998; cuid293 (Box 96, Dvd ref207)
    Ricardo Alarcón is a Cuban politician who served as Cuba's representative to the United Nations and President of Cuba's National Assembly.
    This video features a portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón. The recording does not start at the beginning and appears to only contain a portion of a larger interview. In this portion, Alarcón addresses Estela Bravo's questions about criticism of Cuba's lack of free press by comparing Cuba's press with privately owned newspapers in the United States. He criticizes the United States electoral system, which he contrasts with Cuban local elections. In the second half of the interview he talks about Cuba's role in Latin America, discussing both support for the Cuban government and opposition from what he describes as counter-revolutionary movements. He also talks about the significance of Fidel Castro's beard and his predictions for Cuba's future after Castro's presidency.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:51.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid294 (Box 96, Dvd ref215)
    This portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón begins with a discussion about Cuba in years before the overthrow of Fulgencio Batista's government. He discusses his memories of the revolution and the reaction of many Cubans to the revolution. He talks about the political trials following the revolution, and defends the actions of the new government. Estela Bravo asks Alarcón to describe what he views as the biggest successes and failures in the 40 years since the revolution, and Alarcón describes several domestic policies. They also discuss the ration booklets issued by the Cuban government, and Alarcón criticizes inequality in the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:09.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo and Juanita Vera García, circa 1995-2000; cuid295 (Box 96, Dvd ref1048)
    This video features segments of two separate interviews. The first interview features Cuban politician Ricardo Alarcón. In this brief segment, Alarcón discusses Fidel Castro's personal appearance as a symbol of the revolution, the numerous assassination attempts made against Castro over the years, and the reasons many powerful people have expressed interest in meeting him. At minute 12:42 the footage changes to an interview with Castro's translator Juanita Vera García. García discusses how she became Castro's translator, and talks about what it is like to travel with Castro and act as interpreter for some of his long public speeches.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:09.
  - de Allende, Hortensia Bussi: Interview, circa 1996; cuid17916 (Box 77, Dvd ref244)
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1, 1997 June 5
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17917 (Box 69, Cassette ref893)
      Juan Almeida Bosque (1927-2009) was an important figure in the Cuban Revolution and later a Cuban official. He was the only Afro-Cuban to participate in the attack on the Moncada Barracks in 1953, and was also among the revolutionaries who participated in the 1956 Granma Yacht landing. He was later appointed the commander of the Third Front. During the US-sponsored Bay of Pigs operation in April 1961, Almeida commanded the Cuban military's Central Army. Later a prominent figure in the Communist Party of Cuba, Almeida was, at the time of his death, Vice-President of the Cuban Council of State and its third ranking member.
      This interview is in Spanish. Juan Almeida, who met Fidel Castro in 1952, shares personal stories about his relationship with Castro and talks about his earliest memories of the political situation in Cuba leading up to the revolution.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:53.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17918
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2, 1997 June 5
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17919 (Box 69, Cassette ref894)
      In this part of the interview, Almeida discusses the Cuban revolution, including his memories of the Moncada attack and the Granma landing.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:11:45.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17920
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3, 1997 June 5
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17921 (Box 69, Cassette ref895)
      In this portion of the interview Juan Almeida shares stories about Fidel's relationships with such figures as Che Guevara and Camilo Cienfuegos. He also provides other anecdotes and concludes with a discussion about his personal relationship with Fidel Castro.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:33:22.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17922
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4, 1997 June 5
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17923 (Box 69, Cassette ref896)
      In this portion Juan Almeida talks about Fidel Castro as a symbol of the revolution, briefly discussing the significance of Castro's beard. He also talks about Castro's views of justice, his support of Angolan independence, and the anti-apartheid struggle in South Africa. He later discusses his feelings surrounding Castro's failing health.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:04:56.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17924
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 1 1st Part), 1996 June 27; cuid17925 (Box 70, Cassette ref913, Box 85, Dvd ref913)
    Born Alicia Ernestina de la Caridad Martinez Hoya, Alicia Alonso (1921 - ) is a Cuban prima ballerina and choreographer. She and her husband lived in New York City for a time where she trained at the School of American Ballet. In 1959 they returned to Cuba. Fidel Castro invited her to head a new dance school (Ballet Nacional de Cuba).
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:36.
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 1 2nd Part), 1996 June 27; cuid17926 (Box 70, Cassette ref914, Box 85, Dvd ref914)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:03:09.
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 2 1st Part) with Ramon Castro, 1996 June 27; cuid17927 (Box 70, Cassette ref915, Box 85, Dvd ref915)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:24:30.
  - Andreas, Duane: Interview, 1996 October 9; cuid17929 (Box 62, Cassette ref1043)
    Duane O. Andreas is a US business executive and former chairman and CEO of Archer Daniels Midland (ADM).
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17930 (Box 77, Dvd ref218)
    Francisco Gonzales Aruca (1941-2013) was a Cuban-American economist. He was a student at a Jesuit school in Havana at the time of the Cuban Revolution. He joined the counterrevolution and was arrested in 1961 by the Castro government. His political ideology later shifted in favor of the Cuban government, and he started the company Marazul Charters in New York with a goal of uniting fractured Cuban families.
    In this interview Francisco Aruca discusses people's polarized views of Fidel Castro. He discusses his own feelings about Castro, and spends some time talking about Castro's curiosity for politics. In the interview Estela Bravo asks Aruca about the slogan "No Castro, No Problem." Aruca talks about what he believes are problems with the sentiments behind the slogan, and suggests that in the present political climate, Cuba would be destabilized without Castro.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:46.
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17931 (Box 69, Cassette ref885, Box 85, Dvd ref885)
    The initial 14 minutes feature footage of Aruca at work on the radio program Ayer en Miami. The remainder of the video is an interview of Aruca by Estela Bravo.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:00.
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17932 (Box 9, Cassette ref70)
  - Aruca, Francisco: Footage at radio station, 1996 October 1; cuid17933 (Box 70, Cassette ref883, Box 84, Dvd ref883)
  - Aruca, Francisco: Footage, making telephone calls at radio station, 1996; cuid17934 (Box 70, Cassette ref884, Box 84, Dvd ref884)
  - Aruca, Francisco: Opinions about Canal 51 Report on Estela Bravo, circa 2000; TW_TAM_616_ER_4 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_4)
  - Barnet, Miguel: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17935 (Box 68, Cassette ref853, Box 84, Dvd ref853)
    Estela Bravo interviews Miguel Barnet, Cuban writer, novelist, and ethnographer. The interview is mostly in Spanish, but Estela Bravo speaks English at times.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:14:23.
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview, 1996 August 12; cuid17936 (Box 68, Cassette ref857, Box 84, Dvd ref857)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:10:48.
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview, 1996 August 11; cuid17937 (Box 70, Cassette ref856, Box 85, Dvd ref856)
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview, 1996 August 10; cuid296 (Box 86, Dvd ref18)
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview (part 2), 1996; cuid297 (Box 62, Cassette ref1057, Box 96, Dvd ref1057)
    This video contains portions of an interview with singer Harry Belafonte and his wife Julie Robinson. The interview begins with an anecdote about Belafonte bringing Fidel Castro a gift of cheese, and the caution with which Castro's body guards viewed the gift in light of the numerous assassination attempts that have been made against Castro. The bulk of the interview focuses on Belafonte's travels to Cuba with his family. He discusses his musical performances, and his children's enjoyment of Cuban culture. Robinson discusses bringing her parents to Cuba, and their request to be buried there after they died.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:41.
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview (part 3), 1996; cuid298 (Box 96, Dvd ref217)
    This video contains the last portion of an interview with Harry Belafonte and his wife Julie Robinson. In this short segment they discuss their admiration for Fidel Castro. After the interview concludes the tape shows several still images of Castro and Belafonte.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:02:56.
  - Benn, Tony: Interview (part 1), 1996 March 16; cuid17938 (Box 77, Dvd ref147)